ALL DRACULA’S CHILDREN

Dan Simmons

We flew to Bucharest almost as soon as the shooting had stopped, landing at Otopeni Airport just after midnight on December 29, 1989. As the semi-official “International Assessment Contingent,” the six of us—all men—were hurried past the confused milling about that had passed for Customs since the revolution, and then herded aboard an ONT bus for the nine-mile drive into town. Father Paul, our contingent’s token cleric, pointed at two bullet holes in the rear window of the bus, but Dr. Aimslea topped that simply by pointing out the window as we entered the lighted circular drive leaving the terminal.

Soviet-style tanks sat along the main thoroughfare where cabs normally would be waiting, their long muzzles pointed toward the entrance to the airport drive. Sandbagged emplacements lined the highway and airport rooftops, and the sodium-vapor lamps yellowly illuminated the helmets and rifles of soldiers on guard duty while throwing their faces into deep shadow. Other men, some in regular army uniforms and others in the ragtag clothing of the revolutionary militia, lay sleeping alongside the tanks. For a second the illusion of sidewalks littered with the bodies of Romania’s dead was perfect and I held my breath, exhaling slowly only when I saw one of the bodies stir and another light a cigarette.

“They fought off several counterattacks by loyalist troops and Securitate forces last week,” whispered Don Westler, our political contact from the Embassy. His tone suggested that it was an embarrassing topic, like sex.

Radu Fortuna, the little man who had been introduced to us in the terminal as our guide and liaison with the transitional government, turned in his seat and grinned broadly as if he was not embarrassed by either sex or politics. “They kill many Securitate,” he said loudly, his grin growing even wider. “Three times Ceausescu’s people tried to take airport . . . three times they get killed.”

Don Westler nodded and smiled, obviously uncomfortable with the conversation, but Dr. Aimslea leaned into the aisle. Light from the last of the sodium-vapor lamps illuminated his bald head in the seconds before we entered the darkness of the empty highway. “So Ceausescu’s regime is really over?” he said to Fortuna.

I could see only the slightest gleam from the Romanian’s grin in the sudden darkness. “Ceausescu is over, yes, yes,” he said. “They take him and that bitch-cow of a wife in Tirgoviste, you know . . . have, how you call it . . . trial.” Radu Fortuna laughed again, a sound which somehow sounded both childish and cruel. I found myself shivering a bit in the darkness. The bus was not heated.

“They have trial,” continued Fortuna, “and prosecutor say ‘You both crazy?’ You see, if Ceausescu and Mrs. Ceausescu crazy, then maybe the army just send them away in mental hospital for hundred years, like our Russian friends do. You know? But Ceausescu say, ‘What? What? Crazy . . . How dare you! That is obscene provocation!’ And his wife, she say, ‘How can you say this to the Mother of your nation?’ So prosecutor say, ‘OK, you neither one crazy. Your own mouth say.’ And then the soldiers, they draw straws so many want to be the ones. Then the lucky ones, they take Ceausescus out in courtyard and shoot them in heads many times.” Fortuna chuckled warmly, as if remembering a favorite anecdote. “Yes, regime over,” he said to Dr. Aimslea. “Maybe a few thousand Securitate, they don’t know it yet and still shooting peoples, but that will be over soon. Bigger problem is, what to do with one out of three peoples who spy for old government, heh?”

Fortuna chuckled again, and in the sudden glare from an oncoming army truck, I could see his silhouette as he shrugged. There was a thin layer of condensation turning to ice on the inside of the windows now. My fingers were stiff with the cold and I could barely feel my toes in the absurd Bally dress shoes I had put on that morning. I scraped at some of the ice on my window as we entered the city proper.

“I know that you are all very important peoples from the West,” said Radu Fortuna, his breath creating a small fog that rose toward the roof of the bus like an escaping soul. “But I am afraid I forget some names.”

Don Westler did the introductions. “Dr. Aimslea is with the World Health Organization . . . Father Gerald Paul is here representing both the Archdiocese of Greater Boston and the Save the Children Foundation . .

“Ah, good to have priest here,” said Fortuna, and I heard something that may have been irony in his voice.

“Dr. Leonard Paxley, Professor Emeritus of Economics at Princeton University,” continued Westler. “Winner of the 1978 Nobel Prize in Economics.”

Fortuna bowed toward the old academic. Paxley had not spoken at all during the flight from Frankfurt and now he seemed lost in his oversized coat and folds of muffler: an old man in search of a park bench.

“We welcome you,” said Fortuna, “even though our country have no economy at present moment . . .”

“Goddamn, is it always this cold here?” came the voice from deep in the folds of wool. The Nobel Prize-winning Professor Emeritus stamped his small feet. “This is cold enough to freeze the nuts off a bronze bulldog.”

“And Mr. Carl Berry representing American Telegraph and Telephone,” continued Westler quickly.

The pudgy businessman next to me puffed his pipe, removed it, nodded in Fortuna’s direction, and went back to smoking the thing as if it were a necessary source of heat. I had a moment’s mad vision of the seven of us in the bus huddled around the glowing embers in Berry’s pipe.

“And Mr. Harold Winston Palmer,” said Westler, gesturing in my direction, “Vice President in charge of European markets for . . .”

“Yesss,” said Radu Fortuna, his voice holding approximately the same intonations of hunger that one imagines a python would express mere seconds before devouring its prey. “I know the corporation which Monsieur Palmer represents . . .”

Of course he did. We are one of the largest corporations in the world and if you are an American, you own . . . or have owned . . . one of our major products. If you are Romanian, you dream of owning one.

“You have been in Romania before, I believe, Mr. Palmer?”

I could see Fortuna’s eyes glowing as we reached the lighted part of the city. I am old enough to have been part of the Occupation force in Germany shortly after the war. The scene beyond Fortuna was like that. There were more tanks in Palace Square, black hulks which one would have thought deserted heaps of cold metal if the turret of one had not tracked us as our bus passed by. There were the sooty corpses of burned-out autos and at least one armored personnel carrier that was now only a piece of scorched steel. We turned left and went past the Central University Library, its gold dome and ornate roof now collapsed between soot-streaked and pockmarked walls.

“Yes,” I said, “I have been here before.”

Fortuna leaned toward me. “And perhaps this time your company will open a plant here, yes?”

“Perhaps.”

Fortuna’s gaze did not leave me. “We work very cheap here,” he whispered so softly that I doubt if anyone else except Carl Berry could hear him. “Very cheap. Labor is very cheap here. Life is very cheap here.”

We had turned left off of the empty Calea Victorei, right again on Boulevard Nicholai Bălcesěu, and now the bus screeched to a halt in front of the tallest building in the city, the 22-story Intercontinental Hotel.

“In the morning, gentlemens,” said Fortuna, rising, gesturing the way toward the lighted foyer, “we will see the new Romania. I wish you dreamless sleeps.”

Our group spent the next day meeting with “officials” in the interim government, mostly members of the recently cobbled-together National Salvation Front. The day was so dark that the automatic streetlights came on along the broad Bulevardul N. Bălcesěu and Bulevardul Republicii. The buildings were not heated . . . or at least not perceptibly . . . and the men and women we spoke with looked much the same in their oversized, drab wool coats. By the end of the day we had spoken to a Giurescu, two Tismaneanu, one Boroşoiu who turned out not to be a spokesman for the new government after all . . . he was arrested moments after we left him . . . several generals including Popescu, Lupoi, and Diurgiu, and finally the real leaders, which included Petre Roman, prime minister in the transitional government, and Ion Iliescu and Dumitru Mazilu, who had been President and Vice President in the Ceausescu regime.

Their message was the same: we had the run of the nation and any recommendations we could make to our various constituencies for help would be eternally appreciated.

Returning to the Intercontinental that evening, we watched as a crowd of people—most, it looked, office workers leaving the stone hives of the downtown for the day—beat and pummeled three men and a woman. Radu Fortuna smiled and pointed to the broad plaza in front of the hotel where the crowd was growing larger. “There . . . in University Square last week . . . when peoples come to demonstrate with singing, you know? Army tanks roll over persons, shoot more. Those probably be Securitate informers.”

Before the van rolled under the stone overhang of the hotel, we caught a glimpse of uniformed soldiers leading away the probable informers, encouraging them with the butts of their automatic weapons while the crowd continued to spit and strike them.

“Can’t make an omelette without breaking a few eggs,” muttered our Professor Emeritus, while Father Paul glared at him and Radu Fortuna chuckled appreciatively.

“You’d think Ceausescu would have been better prepared for a siege,” Dr. Aimslea said after dinner that evening. We had stayed in the dining room because it seemed warmer than our own rooms. Waiters and a few military men moved aimlessly through the large space. The reporters had finished their dinner quickly, with a maximum of noise, and left soon after to wherever reporters go to drink and be cynical.

Radu Fortuna had joined us for coffee and now he showed his patented, gap-toothed grin. “You want to see how prepared, Ceausescu, he was?”

Aimslea, Father Paul, and I agreed that we would like to see. Carl Berry decided to go to his room to get a call through to the States and Dr. Paxley followed him, grumbling about getting to bed early. Fortuna led the three of us out into the cold and down shadowed streets to the soot-blackened shell of the presidential palace. A militia man stepped out of the shadows, raised an AK-47, and barked a challenge, but Fortuna spoke quietly and we were allowed to pass.

There were no lights in the palace except for occasional fires in barrels where militia men and regular soldiers slept or huddled to keep warm. Furniture was tossed everywhere, drapes had been ripped from twenty-foot-tall windows, papers littered the floor, and the formal tiles were smeared with dark streaks. Fortuna led us down a narrow hall, through a series of what appeared to be private residential rooms, and stopped at what seemed to be an unmarked closet. Inside the four-foot square closet, there was nothing but three lanterns on a shelf. Fortuna lighted the lanterns, handed one to Aimslea and one to me, and then touched the molding above the back wall. A sliding panel opened to a stone staircase.

The next half hour was dreamlike, almost hallucinatory. The stairway led down to echoing chambers from which a maze of stone tunnels and other stairways branched. Fortuna led us deep into this maze, our lights reflecting off the curved ceilings and slick stones.

“My God,” muttered Dr. Aimslea after ten minutes of this, “these go for miles.”

“Yes, yes,” smiled Radu Fortuna. “Many miles.”

There were storerooms with automatic weapons on shelves, gas masks hanging from hooks; there were command centers with radios and television monitors sitting there in the dark, some destroyed as if madmen with axes had vented their wrath on them, some still covered with clear plastic and waiting only for their operators to turn them on; there were barracks with bunks and stoves and kerosene heating units which we eyed with envy. Some of the barracks looked untouched, others obviously had been the site of panicked evacuation or equally panicked firefights. There was blood on the walls and floors of one of these chambers, the streaks more black than red in the light of our hissing lanterns.

There were still bodies in the farther reaches of the tunnels, some lying in pools of water dripping from overhead hatches, others tumbled behind hastily erected barricades at the junction of the underground avenues. The stone vaults smelled like a meat locker.

“Securitate,” said Fortuna and spat on one of the brown-shirted men lying face down in a frozen pool. “They fled like rats down here and we finished them like rats. You know?”

Father Paul made the sign of the cross and crouched next to one of the men for a long moment, praying silently. Dr. Aimslea said, “But Ceausescu did not retreat to this . . . redoubt?”

“No.” Fortuna smiled.

The doctor looked around in the hissing white light. “For God’s sake why not? If he’d marshalled an organized resistance down here, he could have held out for months.”

Fortuna shrugged. “Instead, the monster, he fled by helicopter. He flied . . . no? Flew, yes . . . he flew to Tirgoviste, seventy kilometers from here, you know? There other peoples see him and his bitch-cow wife get in car. They catch.”

Dr. Aimslea held his lantern at the entrance to another tunnel from which a terrible stench now blew. The doctor quickly pulled back the light. “But I wonder why . . .”

Fortuna stepped closer and the harsh light illuminated an old scar on his neck that I had not noticed before. “They say his . . . advisor . . . the Dark Advisor . . . told him not to come here.” He smiled.

Father Paul tried to smile. “The Dark Advisor. It sounds as if his counselor was the devil.”

Radu Fortuna nodded. “Worse, Father.”

Dr. Aimslea grunted. “Did this devil escape? Or was he one of those poor buggers we saw back there?”

Our guide did not answer but entered one of the four tunnels branching off there. A stone stairway led upward. “To the National Theater,” he said softly, waving us ahead of him. “It was damaged but not destroyed. Your hotel is next door.”

The priest, the doctor, and I started up, lantern light throwing our shadows fifteen feet high on the curved stone walls above. Father Paul stopped and looked down at Fortuna. “Aren’t you coming?”

The little guide smiled and shook his head. “Tomorrow, we take you where it all began. Tomorrow we go to Transylvania.”

Father Paul gave the doctor and me a smile. “Transylvania,” he repeated. “Shades of Bela Lugosi.” He turned back to say something to Fortuna but the little man was gone. Not even the echo of footfalls or shimmer of lantern light showed which tunnel he had taken.

We flew to Timişoara, a city of about 300,000 in western Transylvania, suffering the flight in an old recycled Tupolev turbo-prop now belonging to Tarom, the state airline. We were lucky; the daily flight was delayed only an hour and a half. We flew through cloud for most of the way and there were no interior lights on the plane, but that did not matter because there were neither flight attendants nor the interruption of a meal or snack. Dr. Paxley grumbled most of the way, but the scream of the turbo-props and the groaning of metal as we bounced and bucked our way through updrafts and storm clouds muffled most of his complaints.

Just as we took off, seconds before entering the clouds, Fortuna leaned across the aisle and pointed out the window to a snow-covered island on a lake that must have been about twenty miles north of Bucharest. “Snagov,” he said, watching my face.

I glanced down, caught a glimpse of a dark church on the island before the clouds obliterated the view, and looked back at Fortuna. “Yes?”

“Vlad Tepes buried there.” Fortuna, pronounced it Vlad Tsepesh.

I nodded. Fortuna went back to reading one of our Time magazines, although how someone could read or concentrate during that wild ride, I will never know. A minute later Carl Berry leaned forward from the seat behind me and whispered, “Who the hell is Vlad Tepes? Someone who died in the fighting?”

The cabin was so dark now that I could barely make out Berry’s face inches from my own. “Dracula,” I said to the AT&T executive.

Berry let out a discouraged sigh and leaned back in his seat, tightening his belt as we began to pitch and bounce in earnest.

“Vlad the Impaler,” I whispered to no one at all.

The electricity had failed, so the morgue was cooled by the simple expedient of opening all of the tall windows. The light was still very thin, as if watered down by the dark green walls and grimy panes of glass and constant low clouds, but was adequate to illuminate the rows of corpses across the tabletops and filling almost every inch of the tiled floors. We had to walk a circuitous path, stepping carefully between bare legs and white faces and bulging bellies, just to join Fortuna and the Romanian doctor in the center of the room. There were at least three or four hundred bodies in the long room . . . not counting ourselves.

“Why haven’t these people been buried?” demanded Father Paul, his scarf raised to his face. His voice was angry. “It’s been at least a week since the murders, correct?”

Fortuna translated for the Timişoaran doctor, who shrugged. Fortuna shrugged. “Eleven days since the Securitate, they do this,” he said. “Funerals soon. The . . . how do you say . . . the authorities here, they want to show the Western reporters and such very important peoples as yourselfs. Look, look.” Fortuna opened his arms to the room in a gesture that was almost proud, a chef showing off the banquet he had prepared.

On the table in front of us lay a corpse of an old man. His hands and feet had been amputated by something not very sharp. There were burns on his lower abdomen and genitals, and his chest showed open scars that reminded me of Viking photos of the rivers and craters of Mars.

The Romanian doctor spoke. Fortuna translated. “He say, the Securitate, they play with acid. You know? And here . . .”

The young woman lay on the floor, fully clothed except for the ripped clothing that extended from her breasts to pubic bone. What I first took for another layer of slashed, red rags, I now realized was the red-rimmed wall of her opened belly and abdomen. The seven-month fetus lay on her lap like a discarded doll. It would have been a boy.

“Here,” commanded Fortuna, stepping through the maze of ankles and gesturing.

The boy must have been about ten. Death and a week or more of freezing cold had expanded and mottled flesh to the texture of bloated, marbled parchment, but the barbed wire around his ankles and wrists was still quite visible. His arms had been tied behind him with such force that the shoulder joints were totally out of their sockets. Flies had been at his eyes and the layer of eggs there made it look as if the child were wearing white goggles.

Professor Emeritus Paxley made a noise and staggered from the room, almost tripping over the bodies set out for display there. One old man’s gnarled hand seemed to tug at the professor’s pant leg as he fled.

Father Paul grabbed Fortuna by his coat front and almost lifted the little man from the floor. “Why in the hell are you showing us this?”

Fortuna grinned. “There is more, Father. Come.”

“They called Ceausescu ‘the vampire’,” said Don Westler, who had flown up later to join us.

“And here in Timişoara is where it started,” said Carl Berry, puffing on his pipe and looking around at the gray sky, gray buildings, gray slush on the street, and gray people moving through the dim light.

“Here in Timişoara is where the final explosion began,” said Westler. “The younger generation has been getting more and more restless for some time. In a real sense, Ceausescu signed his own death warrant by creating that generation.”

“Creating that generation,” repeated Father Paul, frowning. “Explain.”

Westler explained. In the mid-1960’s, Ceausescu had outlawed abortion, discontinued the import of oral contraceptives and IUD’s, and announced that it was a woman’s obligation to the state to have many children. More importantly, his government had offered birth premiums and reduced taxes to those families who obeyed the government’s call for increased births. Couples who had fewer than five children were actually fined as well as heavily taxed. Between 1966 and 1976, said Westler, there had been a forty percent increase in babies born, along with a huge rise in infant mortality.

“It was this surplus of young people in their twenties by the late 1980’s who provided the core of the revolution,” said Westler. “They had no jobs, no chance for a college education . . . not even a chance for decent housing. They were the ones who began the protests in Timişoara and elsewhere.”

Father Paul nodded. “Ironic . . . but appropriate.”

“Of course,” said Westler, pausing near the train station, “most of the peasant families could not afford to raise the extra children . . .”He stopped with that diplomat’s tic of embarrassment.

“So what happened to those children?” I asked. It was only early afternoon but the light had faded to a wintry twilight. There were no streetlights along this section of Timişoara’s main boulevard. Somewhere far down the tracks, a locomotive screamed.

Don Westler shook his head but Radu Fortuna stepped closer. “We take train tonight to Sebeş, Sibiu, Copsa Mica, and Sighişoara,” the smiling Romanian said. “You see where babies go.”

Winter evening became winter night beyond the windows of our train with the slow dying of the light. The train passed through mountains worn smooth and toothless by age—whether they were the Fagaras Range or the lower Bucegi Carpathians, I did not remember from earlier trips—and the dismal sight of huddled villages and sagging farms faded to blackness broken only by the occasional glow of oil lamps through distant windows. I realized with a start that it was New Year’s Eve, the last night of 1989, and that the dawn would bring what was popularly thought of as the last decade of the millennium . . . but beyond the window lay the Seventeenth Century. The only intrusion of the modern age visible in the evening departure from Timişoara had been the occasional military vehicle glimpsed on snow-packed roads and the occasional electric cables snaking above the trees. Then those slim talismans had disappeared and there were only the villages, the oil lamps, the cold, and an occasional rubber-wheeled cart, pulled by horses who seemed more bone than flesh and guided by men hidden in dark wool. Then even the village streets were empty as the train rushed through, stopping nowhere. I realized that some of the villages were totally dark, even though it was not yet ten p.m., and leaning closer, wiping frost from the glass, I saw that the village we were passing now was dead—buildings bulldozed, stone walls demolished, farm homes tumbled down.

“Systematization,” whispered Radu Fortuna, who had appeared silently next to me in the aisle. He was chewing on an onion.

I did not ask for clarification, but our guide and liaison smiled and provided it. “Ceausescu wanted to destroy the old. He break down villages, move thousands of peoples to city places like Victory of Socialism Boulevard in Bucharest . . . kilometers and kilometers of tall apartment buildings. Only buildings, they not finished when he tear down and move peoples there. No heat. No water. No electricity . . . he sell electricity to other countries, you see. So village peoples, they have little house out here, be in family three, maybe four hundreds of years, but now live on ninth floor of bad brick building in strange city . . . no windows, cold wind blow in. Have to carry water a mile, then carry up nine flights of stairs.”

He took a deep bite of the onion and nodded as if satisfied. “Systematization.” He moved on down the smoky aisle.

The mountains passed in the night. I began to doze . . . I had slept little the night before, dreamlessly or otherwise, and I had not slept on the plane the night before that . . . but awoke with a start to find that the Professor Emeritus had taken the seat next to me.

“No goddamn heat,” he whispered, tugging his muffler tighter. “You’d think with all these goddamn peasant bodies and goats and chickens and what have you in this so-called first-class car, that they’d generate some body heat in here, but it’s as cold as Madame Ceausescu’s dear dead tit.”

I blinked at the simile.

“Actually,” said Dr. Paxley in a conspiratorial whisper, “it’s not as bad as they say.”

“The cold?” I said.

“No, no. The economy. Ceausescu may be the only national leader in this century who actually paid off his country’s foreign debt. Of course, he had to divert food, electricity, and consumer goods to other countries to do it, but Romania has no foreign debt at all now. None.”

“Mmmm,” I said, trying to remember the fragments of the dream I’d in my few moments of sleep. Something about blood.

“A one-point-seven billion dollar trade surplus,” muttered Paxley, leaning close enough that I could tell that he’d also had onion for dinner. “And they owe the West nothing and the Russians nothing. Incredible.”

“But the people are starving,” I said softly. Westler and Father Paul were snoring in the seat in front of us.

Paxley waved that away. “Should German reunification come, do you know how much the West Germans are going to have to invest just to retool the infrastructure in the East?” Not waiting for my reply, he went on. “A hundred billion Deutschmarks . . . and that’s just to prime the pump. With Romania, the infrastructure is so pitiful that there’s little to tear down. Just junk the industrial madness that Ceausescu was so proud of, use the cheap labor . . . my God, man, they’re almost serfs . . . and build whatever industrial infrastructure you want. The South Korean model, Mexico . . . it’s wide open for the western corporation that’s willing to take the chance.”

I pretended to doze off again and eventually the Professor Emeritus moved down the aisle to find someone else to explain the economic facts of life to. The villages passed in the darkness as we moved deeper into the Transylvanian mountains.

We arrived in Sebes before dawn and there was some minor official there to take us to the orphanage.

No, orphanage is too kind a word. It was a warehouse, heated no better than the other meatlockers we had been in so far, undecorated except for grimy tile floors and flaking walls painted a vomitous green to eye height and a leprous gray above that. The main hall was at least a hundred meters across.

It was filled with cribs.

Again, the word is too generous. Not cribs, but low metal cages with no tops to them. In the cages were children. Children ranging in age from newborns to ten-year-olds. None seemed capable of walking. All were naked or dressed in filth-caked rags. Many were screaming or weeping silently and the fog of their breath rose in the cold air. Stern-faced women in complicated nurse’s caps stood smoking cigarettes on the periphery of this giant human stockyard, occasionally moving among the cages to brusquely hand a bottle to a child . . . sometime a seven- or eight-year-old child . . . or more frequently to slap one into silence.

The official and the chain-smoking administrator of the “orphanage” snapped a tirade at us which Fortuna did not deign to translate, and then they walked us through the room and slammed open tall doors.

Another room, a larger room, opened into the cold-shrouded distance. Thin morning light fell in shafts onto the cages and faces there. There must have been at least a thousand children in this room, none of them more than two years old. Some were crying, their infant wails echoing in the tiled space, but most seemed too weak and lethargic even to cry as they lay on the thin, excrement-smeared rags. Some lay in the foetal grip of near starvation. Some looked dead.

Radu Fortuna turned and folded his arms. He was smiling. “You see where the babies go, yes?”

In Sibiu we found the hidden children. There were four orphanages in this central Transylvanian city of 170,000, and each orphanage was larger and sadder than the one in Sebes. Dr. Aimslea demanded, through Fortuna, that we be allowed to see the AIDS children.

The administrator of Strada Cetajii Orfelinat 319, a windowless old structure in the shadow of the 16th-century city walls, absolutely refused to acknowledge that there were any AIDS babies. He refused to acknowledge our right to enter the orphanage. He refused, at one point, to acknowledge that he was the administrator of Strada Cetajii Orfelinat 319, despite the stenciling on his office door and the plaque on his desk.

Fortuna showed him our travel papers and authorization forms, co-signed with a personal plea for cooperation from interim Prime Minister Roman, President Iliescu, and Vice President Mazilu.

The administrator sneered, took a drag on his short cigarette, shook his head, and said something dismissive. “My orders come from the Ministry of Health,” Radu Fortuna translated.

It took almost an hour to get through to the capital, but Fortuna finally completed a call to the Prime Minister’s office, who called the Ministry of Health, who promised to call Strada Cetajii Orfelinat 319 immediately. A little over two hours later, the call came, the administrator snarled something at Fortuna, tossed his cigarette butt on dirty tiles littered with them, snapped something at an orderly, and handed a huge ring of keys to Fortuna.

The AIDS ward was behind four sets of locked doors. There were no nurses there, no doctors . . . no adults of any kind. Neither were there cribs; the infants and small children sat on the tile floor or competed to find space on one of half a dozen bare and excrement-stained mattresses thrown against the far wall. They were naked and their heads had been shaved. The windowless room was illuminated by a few naked 40-watt bulbs set thirty or forty feet apart. Some children congregated there in the pools of murky light, raising swollen eyes to them as if to the sun, but most lay in the deep shadows. Older children scuttled on all fours to escape the light as we opened the steel doors.

It was obvious that the floors were hosed down every few days—there were rivulets and streaks along the cracked tiles—and it was just as obvious that no other hygienic efforts had been made. Don Westler, Dr. Paxley, and Mr. Berry turned and fled from the stench. Dr. Aimslea cursed and pounded his fist against a stone wall. Father Paul first wept, then moved from infant to infant, touching their heads, whispering softly to them in a language they did not understand, and lifting them. I had the distinct impression as I watched that most of these children had never been held, perhaps never been touched.

Radu Fortuna followed us into the room. He was not smiling. “Comrade Ceausescu told us that AIDS is a capitalist disease,” he whispered. “Romania has no official cases of AIDS. None.”

“My God, my God,” Dr. Aimslea was muttering as he moved from child to child. “Most of these are in advanced stages of AIDS-related complexes. And suffering from malnutrition and vitamin deficiencies.” He looked up and there were tears gleaming behind his glasses. “How long have they been here?”

Fortuna shrugged. “Most maybe since little babies. Parents put here. Babies not go out of this room, that why so few know to walk. No one to hold them up when they try.”

Dr. Aimslea unleashed a series of curses that seemed to smoke in the chill air. Fortuna nodded.

“But hasn’t anyone documented these . . . this . . . tragedy?” said Dr. Aimslea in a constricted voice.

Now Fortuna smiled. “Oh, yes, yes. Dr. Patrascu from Stefan S. Nicolau Institute of Virology, he say this happening three . . . maybe four years ago. First child he test, was infected. I think six out of next fourteen also sick from AIDS. All cities, all state orphanages he went to, many, many sick childrens.”

Dr. Aimslea rose from shining his pen light in a comatose infant’s eyes. Aimslea grabbed Fortuna by the coat, and for a second I was sure that he was going to strike the little guide in the face. “For Christ’s sake, man, didn’t he tell anyone?”

Fortuna stared impassively at the doctor. “Oh, yes. Dr. Patrascu, he tell Ministry of Health. They say for him to stop immediately. They cancel AIDS seminar Doctor schedule . . . then they burn his minutes and . . . how do you say it? Like little guides for meeting . . . programs. They confiscate printed programs and burn them.”

Father Paul set down a child. The two-year-old’s thin arms strained toward the priest as she made vague, imploring noises—a plea to be lifted again. Father Paul lifted her, held her bald and scabrous head against his cheek. “Goddamn them,” whispered the priest in a tone of benediction. “Goddamn the ministry. Goddamn that sonofabitch downstairs. Goddamn Ceausescu forever. May they all burn in hell.”

Dr. Aimslea stood from where he crouched near a toddler who seemed all ribs and extended belly. “This child is dead.” He turned to Fortuna again. “How in the hell can this happen? There can’t be that many cases of AIDS among the general population yet, can there? Or are these children of drug addicts?”

I could see the other question in the doctor’s eyes: in a nation where the average family could not afford to buy food and where possession of a narcotic was punishable by death, how could there be so many children of drug users?

“Come,” said Fortuna, and led the doctor and me out of that ward of death. Father Paul remained, lifting and touching child after child.

In the “healthy ward” downstairs, differing from the Sebeş orphanage only in size—there must have been a thousand or more children in the endless sea of steel cribs—nurses were moving stolidly from child to child, giving them glass bottles of what looked to be formulized milk, and then, as each child sucked noisily, injecting him or her with a syringe. Then the nurse would wipe the syringe with a rag she carried on her belt, re-insert it in a large vial from her tray, and inject the next child.

“Mother of Christ,” whispered Dr. Aimslea. “You don’t have disposable syringes?”

Fortuna made a gesture with his hands. “A capitalist luxury.”

Aimslea’s face was so red that I thought capillaries were bursting there. “Then what about fucking autoclaves!”

Fortuna shrugged and asked the nearest nurse something. She snapped a reply and went back to her injections. “She say, the autoclave is broken. Has been broken. Sent to Ministry of Health to be fixed,” translated Fortuna.

“How long?” grated Aimslea.

“It broken four years,” said Fortuna after calling the question to the busy woman. She had not bothered to turn around while replying. “She say, that was four years before it sent to the Ministry for repair last year.”

Dr. Aimslea stepped closer to a six- or seven-year-old lying in his crib sucking on his bottle. The formula looked like gray water. “And these are vitamin shots they’re administering?”

“Oh, no,” said Fortuna. “Blood.”

Dr. Aimslea froze, then turned slowly. “Blood?”

“Yes, yes. Adult’s blood. It make little babies strong. Ministry of Health approve . . . they say it is very . . . how do you say . . . advanced medicine.”

Aimslea took a step toward the nurse, then a step toward Fortuna, and then wheeled toward me as if he would kill either of the first two if he got close to them. “Adult’s blood, Palmer. Jesus H. Christ. That was a theory that went out with gaslights and spats. My God, Palmer, don’t they realize . . .”He suddenly turned back toward our guide. “Fortuna, where do they get this . . , adult blood?”

“It donated . . . no, wrong word. Not donated, bought. Those peoples in big cities who have no money at all, they sell blood for babies. Fifteen lei each time.”

Dr. Aimslea made a rough sound in his throat, a noise that soon turned to chuckles. He shaded his eyes with his hand and staggered backward, leaning against a tray filled with bottles of dark liquid. “Paid blood donors,” he whispered to himself. “Street people . . . drug addicts . . . prostitutes . . . and they administer it to infants in the state homes with reusable, non-sterile needles.” The chuckles continued, grew louder. Dr. Aimslea lowered himself to a sitting position on the dirty towels, the hand still over his eyes, laughing deep in his throat. “How many . . .”he started to ask Fortuna. He cleared his throat and tried again. “How many did this Dr. Patrascu estimate were infected with AIDS?”

Fortuna frowned as he tried to remember. “I think maybe he find seventy of the first two thousand. More higher number after that.”

From beneath the visor of his hand, Dr. Aimslea said, “Almost five percent. And how many . . . orphanage children . . . are there?”

Our guide shrugged. “Ministry of Health say maybe two hundred thousand. I think more . . . maybe half a million. Maybe more.”

Dr. Aimslea did not look up or speak again. The deep chuckles grew louder and deeper, and I realized then that they were not chuckles at all, but sobs.

We took the train north through late afternoon light toward Sighişoara. Fortuna had planned one stop in a small town along the way.

“Mr. Palmer, you like Copsa Mica,” he said. “It is for you we see it.”

I did not turn to look at him, but kept my gaze on the demolished villages we were passing. “More orphanages?” I said.

“No, no. I mean, yes . . . there is orphanage in Copsa Mica, but we don’t go there. It is small town . . . six thousand peoples. But it is reason you come to our country, yes?”

I did turn to stare. “Industry?”

Fortuna laughed. “Ah, yes . . . Copsa Mica is most industrious. Like so many of our towns. And this one so close to Sighişoara, where Comrade Ceausescu’s Dark Advisor was born . . .”

I have been to Sighişoara. “Dark Advisor,” I snapped. “What the hell are you saying? That Ceausescu’s advisor was Vlad Tepes?”

Sighişoara is a perfectly preserved medieval town where even the presence of the few autos on the narrow, cobblestoned streets seem an anachronism. The hills surrounding Sighişoara are studded with tumbledown towers and keeps . . . none of them as cinematic as the half dozen intact castles in Transylvania which advertise themselves as Dracula’s castle for impressionable travelers with hard currency . . . but the old house on Piata Muzeului had truly been Vlad Dracula’s home from 1431 to 1435. The last time I had seen it, over a decade earlier, the upstairs had been a restaurant and the basement a wine cellar. “You want me to believe that Vlad Dracul was the Dark Advisor?” I asked, not hiding the contempt in my voice.

Fortuna shrugged and went off in search of something to eat. Dr. Aimslea had overheard the conversation and dropped into the seat next to me. “Do you believe that man?” he whispered. “Now he’s ready to tell you ghost stories about Dracula. Christ!”

I nodded and looked out at the mountains and valleys sliding by in gray monotone. There was a wildness here that I had not seen elsewhere in the world, and I have traveled in more nations than there are in the U.N. The mountainside, deep ravines, and trees seemed malformed, gnarled, like something struggling to escape from a dark Van Gogh painting.

“I wish it were Dracula we had to deal with here,” continued the good doctor. “Think of it, Palmer . . . if our contingent announced that Vlad the Impaler were alive and preying on people in Transylvania, well . . . hell . . . there’d be ten thousand reporters up here. Satellite trucks parked in Sibiu’s town square to bounce back InstaCam reports to every Channel 7 and Channel 4 hometown news market in America. One monster biting a few dozen people, and the world would be galvanized with interest . . . but as it is, tens of thousands of men and women dead, hundreds of thousands of children warehoused and facing . . . goddammit!

I nodded without turning. “The banality of evil,” I whispered.

“What?”

“The banality of evil.” I turned and smiled grimly at the physician. “Dracula would be a story. The plight of hundreds of thousands of victims of political madness, bureaucracy, stupidity . . . this is just an . . . inconvenience.”

We arrived at Copsa Mica just before nightfall, and I realized at once why it was “my” town. Westler, Aimslea, Paxley, and Father Paul stayed on the train for the half-hour layover; only Carl Berry and I had business there. Fortuna led the way.

The village—it was too small to call a town—lay between steep mountain slopes. There was snow on the hillsides, but the snow was black. The icicles which hung from the dark eaves of the buildings were black. Underfoot, the slush along the unpaved roads was a gray and black mixture, and over everything hung a visible pall of black air, as if a million microscopic moths were fluttering in the dying light. Men and women in black coats and shawls moved past us, dragging their heavy carts or leading children by the hand, and the faces of these people were soot black. As we approached the center of the village, I realized that the three of us were wading through a layer of ash and soot at least four inches deep. I have seen active volcanoes in South America and elsewhere, and the ash and midnight skies were the same.

“It is . . . how do you say it . . . auto-tire plant,” said Radu Fortuna, gesturing toward the black industrial complex that filled the end of the valley like some grounded dragon. “It makes black powder for rubber products . . . works twenty-four hours a day. Sky is always like this . . .”He gestured proudly toward the black haze that settled down on everything.

Carl Berry was coughing. “Good Lord, how can people live in this?”

“They not live long,” said Fortuna. “Most old peoples, like you and me, they have lead poisoning. Little childrens have . . . what is word? Always coughing?”

“Asthma,” said Berry.

“Yes, little childrens have asthma. Babies born with hearts which are . . . how do you say, badformed?”

“Malformed,” said Berry.

I stopped a hundred yards from the black fences and black walls of the plant. The village behind us was a sketch of blacks against grays. Even the lamplight did not truly penetrate the soot-blackened windows. “Why is this ‘my town,’ Fortuna?” I said.

He held his hand out toward the factory. The lines in his palm were already black with soot, the cuff of his white shirt a dark gray.

“Ceausescu gone now. Factory no longer have to turn out rubber things for East Germany, Poland, USSR . . . you want? Make things your company want? No . . . how do you say . . . no environmental impactment states, no regulations against making things the way you want, throwing away things where you want. So, you want?”

I stood there in the black snow for a long moment and might have stood there longer if the train had not shrieked its two-minute warning. “Perhaps,” I said. “Just perhaps.”

We trudged back through ash.

Don Westler, Father Paul, Dr. Aimslea, Carl Berry, and our Professor Emeritus Dr. Leonard Paxley took a morning Tarom flight back to Bucharest from Sighişoara. I stayed behind. The morning was dark, with heavy clouds that moved up the valley and shrouded the surrounding ridges in shifting haze. The city walls with their eleven stone towers seemed to blend their gray stones with the gray skies, sealing the medieval town under a solid dome of gloom. After a late breakfast, I filled my Thermos, left the old town square, and climbed the hundred and seventy-two steps of the Covered Stairway to the house on Piata Muzeului. The iron doors to the wine cellar were closed, the narrow doors to the first floor sealed with heavy shutters. An old man sitting in the square across the street told me that the restaurant had been closed for several years, that the State had considered turning the house into a museum but then decided that foreign guests would not pay hard currency to see a run-down house . . . not even one where Vlad Dracul had lived five centuries before. The tourists preferred the large old castles a hundred miles east, nearer Bucharest; castles which had been erected centuries after Vlad Tepes had disappeared.

I went back across the street, waited until the old man had fed his pigeons and left, and then I tugged off the heavy bar holding the shutters in place. The panes on the doors were as black as the soul of Copsa Mica. The doors were locked, but I scratched at the centuries-old glass.

Fortuna opened the door and led me in. Most of the tables and chairs had been stacked on a rough bar, cobwebs running from them to the smoke-blackened rafters, but Fortuna had pulled one table down and set it in the middle of the stone floor. He dusted off the two chairs before we sat.

“Did you enjoy the tour?” he asked in Romanian.

“Da,” I said, and continued in the same language, “but I felt that you overdid it a bit.”

Fortuna shrugged. He went behind the bar, dusted off two pewter tankards, and brought them back to the table.

I cleared my throat. “Did you recognize me at the airport as a member of the family?” I said.

My erstwhile guide showed his grin. “Of course.”

I frowned at this. “How? I spend as much time in the sun as I can to keep my tan. I was born in America.”

“Your manners,” said Fortuna, letting the Romanian word roll off his tongue. “Your manners are much too good for an American.”

I sighed. Fortuna reached below the table and brought forth a wineskin, but I made a gesture and lifted the Thermos from my overcoat pocket. I poured for both of us and Radu Fortuna nodded, as serious as I had seen him during the past three days. We toasted.

“Skoal,” I said. The drink was very good, fresh, still at body temperature and nowhere near that point of coagulation where a certain bitterness sets in.

Fortuna drained his tankard, wiped his mustache, and nodded his appreciation. “Your company will buy the plant in Copsa Mica?” he asked.

“Yes.”

“And the other plants . . . in other Copsa Micas?”

“Yes,” I said. “Or our consortium will underwrite European investment in it.”

Fortuna smiled. “The investors in the family will be happy. It will be twenty-five years before this country will be able to afford the luxury of worrying about the environment . . . and the people’s health.”

“Ten years,” I said. “Environmental awareness is contagious.”

Fortuna made a gesture with his hands and shoulders . . . a peculiarly Transylvanian gesture which I had not seen in years.

“Speaking of contagious,” I said, “the orphanage situation seems insane.”

The small man nodded. Dim light from the door behind me lighted his brow. Beyond him there was only blackness. “We do not have the luxury of your American plasma . . . private bloodbanks. The State had to provide a reservoir.”

“But the AIDS . . .” I began.

“Will be contained,” said Fortuna. “Thanks to the humanitarian impulses of your Dr. Aimslea and Father Paul. Within the month, your American television will air ‘specials’ on 60 Minutes and 20/20 and whatever other programs you have created since I visited last. Americans are sentimental. There will be a public outcry. Aid will flow from all those groups and from rich people who have nothing better to do with their time. Families will adopt, pay a fortune for sick children to be flown to the States, and local television stations will interview mothers weeping with happiness.”

I nodded.

“Your American health workers . . . and British . . . and West German . . . will flock to the Carpathians, and the Bucegis, and the Fagaras . . . and we will ’discover’ many other orphanages and hospitals, many other of these isolation wards. Within two years it will be contained.”

I nodded again. “But they’re liable to take a sizable amount of your . . . reservoir . . . with them,” I said softly.

Fortuna smiled and shrugged again. “There are more. Always more. Even you know that in your land of teenage runaways and missing children’s photos on milk cartons, no?”

I finished my drink, got up, and paced toward the light. “Those days are over,” I said. “Survival equals moderation. All of the family must learn that someday.” I turned back toward Fortuna and my voice held more anger than I had expected. “Otherwise, what? The contagion again? A growth of the family more rapid than cancer, more virulent than AIDS? Contained, we are in balance. Left to . . . propagate . . . there will be only the hunters with no prey, as doomed to starvation as those rabbits on Easter Island years ago.”

Fortuna held up both hands, palms outward. “We must not argue, my cousin. We know that. It is why Ceausescu had to go. It is why he was not allowed into his tunnels, to reach the triggers that would have brought Bucharest down.”

“So there was a Dark Advisor,” I said, my voice little more than a whisper.

Fortuna smiled. “Oh, yes.”

It took me half a minute before I could say the word. “Father?”

Fortuna rose, walked to the dark hall where a darker stairway waited. He gestured upward and led the way into the dark, my guide one final time.

The bedroom had been one of the larger storerooms above the tourist restaurant. Five centuries ago it might have been a bedroom. His bedroom.

The figure lying there under thick tapestry-like covers and between gray sheets was so old as to be outside of age, beyond gender. The shutters were drawn, dust and cobwebs filled the room everywhere except where the head and shoulders lay on the pearl-white pillow, but there was a trail through the dust where attendants had trod, and just enough light filtering through the chinks in the shutters to allow one’s eyes to adapt.

“My God,” I whispered.

Fortuna smiled. “Yes.”

I drew closer, went to one knee despite myself. He was barely recognizable from the photographs others in the family had shown me. The high forehead was still dominant, the deep-set eyes and sharp, noble cheekbones still visible, but nothing else was the same. Age had turned the flesh to yellow parchment, the hair to cobwebs, the eyes to egg-white marbles sunk deep in pools of dead skin. The teeth were gone. His hands lay above the blankets; they reminded me of a mummified monkey’s paw I had seen in the Royal Museum in Cairo many years before. The fingernails were yellow and at least six inches long.

I leaned forward and kissed the ring on his right hand. “Father,” I whispered, feeling my flesh crawl with revulsion and adoration.

There came a rattling sound deep in the thing’s chest and a fog of rancid air escaped from the hole of a mouth.

I stood. It was then, as my eyes adapted to the dark, that I saw the lesions and scales, the thousand sores and scabs and rivulets of rotting skin that showed the presence of Kaposi’s sarcoma in its final stages. I did not need to be Dr. Aimslea to recognize the telltale signs; all of us in the family are experts in AIDS and its symptoms. We fear it more than the stake or the auto-da-fe.

“He contracted it here?” I whispered, realizing how silly it was to whisper even as I did so. The thing on the bed would never hear again.

Radu Fortuna chuckled. “I wish it were so. Father was very careless. Remember, the HIV virus is a retrovirus. A contagion from millennia ago. The scientists do not know from whence it came, or how it was spread to humans.”

I took a step away from the bed, my skin prickling with horror. “Father?”

Fortuna shrugged. “He was careless. Long ago. The family begged him not to go, but he was certain that Africa was a perfect place for his . . . retirement. A place to start a new branch of the family. To relive the glories of his Carpathian past.”

I backed away until the doorframe stopped me. “He was mad.”

“Oh, yes.” Fortuna walked to the bed and covered the figure there so that the hands were out of sight and only the beak of a nose and rotting forehead remained above the covers. “The family pursued him across four continents before we could persuade him to come home. By then . . . he had no choice.”

I shook my head. The room seemed to waver, to become insubstantial, and I realized that I was crying. Brusquely, I wiped away the tears. “I did not know.”

“It does not matter,” said Fortuna. “Western medicine and western science and western technology will beat this, just as it has beaten all other plagues. We count on it. The family has removed all barriers . . . national, ideological . . . so this can be true.”

I nodded again and rested my hand on Fortuna’s arm as we moved toward the staircase. On some internal impulse I turned back to the room, stood alone a second at the doorway, and genuflected once toward the darkness there before going back to my guide and advisor.

Together, my hand on his strong shoulder, we left the old world behind and went downstairs to greet the new.